If he had not attacked Ukraine, there would
Если бы он не напал на Украину войны бы
not have been a war. It turns out that now
не было получается сейчас из этой войны
Russians in Russia and Ukrainians in
умирают россияне в России и украинцы в
Ukraine are dying from this war, yes, that is, it turns out that Putin
Украине да то есть получается Путин
is playing to the tune of Great Britain and the
играет под дудку Великобритании и
United States. No,
США Нет
of course not. Why is he then on Well, you
конечно так А зачем он тогда на Ну вы же
understand that there was a provocation
понимаете что была провокация
What
Какая
Hello, where are you from
Здравствуйте Вы откуда
? I know, I’m from Moldova, I’m from Chisinau. And
ша Я знаю я из Молдовы сам Из Кишинёва А
you’re from Russia,
вы из России
where is Moscow from? Moscow
откуда моско о москов
City and I looked there, it’s not safe, there
Сити и я смотрел там не не безопасно там
are flights to Moscow City in general. We’re
прилёты бывают в Москов Сити вообще Мы
from the Orenburg region,
из Оренбургской области
Orsk,
Орск
Yes, my mother is from Orsk,
Да у меня мама из Орска
the girls are yes.  I just I
девчонки это да я просто я вот в
don’t know in the Orenburg region, just
Оренбургской области не знаю просто
Orenburg and Orsk My mother is from there
Оренбург и Орск У меня мама оттуда
In short I was born there I was 2
Короче мне было Я родился там мне было 2
years old and they took me away from there I don’t remember
года и меня оттуда увезли я не помню
anything but I was born in Orsk I was born in
ничего но я родился в Орске родился в
Orsk you know It’s on my
Орске понимаете У меня у меня в
certificate  about birth he writes
свидетельстве о рождения так и пишет
like the
типа
RSFSR Orsk like the Russian Soviet
РСФСР Орск типа Российская Советская
Federative Socialist Republic
Федеративная Социалистическая Республика
Yes, the city of Orsk Holy [ __ ], it’s absolutely class
Да город Орск [__] блин вообще класс
And who are you
А вы там на кого
studying to be a translator,
учитесь переводщик
I’m not studying I’m also a translator I’m a lawyer
я не учусь Я тоже переводчик Я юрист
lawyer a translator And the guy TC the
юрист переводчик А пацан ТЧ
girl in the center of the translation And I understood the translation
девушка по центру перево А понял перево
In short, that’s it  translators are lawyers and don’t
Короче все переводчики юристы и не
study I understood I understood how it was that
учатся понял понял понял как та это у
you had a flood and last year Damn
вас же потоп был да в прошлом году Блин
I just watched it on TV It
я короче смотрел это по телевизору Мне
hurt so bad it was just crap
так больно короче аж было просто капец
Well I’m with people people it was flooded that there was a
Ну я с люди люди было затоплено что там
woman sitting on the roof with a cat  and in short,
женщина сидела на крыше с котом и короче
and waited, like I was filming a video, he says I don’t
и ждали типа снимала видео говорит Не
know when they’ll release us, like he
знаю когда нас это освободят типа
says, it’s a bummer, but you weren’t
говорит капец а вас не
flooded, I was flooded. Tell me, I’m
затопило меня затопило А расскажите мне
just curious, well, I was flooded, well, it’s a
просто интересно ну меня затопило что ну
bummer at home, we had a two-story house, the
там капец дома был у нас двухэтажный дом
first floor was completely flooded, but
первый этаж прям полностью затопила но
we made it there  raise the equipment to the second floor,
мы успели там поднять на второй этаж
took out the cats and dogs
технику вывезли котов собак
there, they paid us 60,000 for a major
там нам заплатили 60.000 на капитальный
overhaul for 60,000 600 dollars, something will
ремонт за 60.000 600 долларов там что-то
be repaired there, so I bought a coat and it
отремонтирует вот я пальто купила а
was repaired. For what money
отремонтировали За какие деньги
then
тогда
millions Well, where did they get this money then
миллионов Ну где взяли эти деньги тогда
or is it from personal from personal of course there of
или это из личных из личных конечно там
course  these sellers of building materials
конечно эти продавцы стройматериалов
probably got up, well, well, my
поднялись наверное капец да ну у меня у
parents have building materials,
родителей стройматериалы
uh, these boards are wood,
ээ этот доски лес
well, they were just flooded, too, it turns out
э то их как раз затопило тоже получается
not By the way, it didn’t flood And we didn’t
не Кстати это не не затопило И мы не
raise the prices for building materials, well,
поднимали цены на стройматериалы вот ну
precisely because of the flood Well, they were sold out
именно из-за потопа Да ну их раскупили
at  -everyone, yes,
по-любому все да
probably whoever they bought Well, all
наверное кого купили Ну все
the building materials were probably bought up, yes yes
стройматериалы раскупили наверное да да
dada dadada there was a big queue there,
дада дадада там прямо очередь была
you got yourself into a flood, like for repairs
вы себе отбили на потоп типа на ремонт
Well, you can say so And how come your
Ну можно и так сказать А как там у вас
guys aren’t being drafted into the
ребят не забирают в
army, they
армию
punched for no mobilization  now she’s not
пробили на с не мобилизация сейчас не
going, but she has some acquaintances in
идёт а есть какие-то знакомые на
s Well, my friend’s
с Ну у подруги
father is a university student,
отец уча вке
well, it’s like they’re relatives, but we’re with them.
ну как бы это родственники но мы с ними
I don’t know them. It turns out that this is my mother’s
Я не знаком с ними получается Это у мамы
second cousin. She lives in Orsk. Yes, and it’s
троюродная сестра Она в Орске живёт Да и
like she sometimes writes off with her  then
как бы она иногда с ней списывается то
she says that her husband, her husband,
она говорит что её мужа её мужа то
was taken to the second one, in short, and he’s
забрали в д втором на сво короче и он
missing a leg
без ноги
now, and now he’s going nuts. And you have some acquaintances who are
сейчас [__] А вас какие-то знакомые
wounded, dead,
раненые погибшие
no wounded, there’s one for a couple under a
есть нет раненые Есть один паре по
contract, and he was in the hospital with a wound;
контракту и с ранением лежал в госпитале
he was sent to Moscow for three months.
его в Москву направили месяца три
in my opinion, this is what happened to him, to be honest, I
по-моему вот а что случило с ним честно
didn’t communicate with him on this topic, but
сказать не общалась с ним на эту тему но
the bullet seems to be like that, so wait and this If I
пулевое вроде как так подожди а это Если
did, then he’s young, relatively Why did
общался то он молодой относительно Зачем
he sign for a contract? He’s young,
он на контракт пошёл он Молодой ему года
22 years old, in my opinion, if I’m not
22 по-моему если я не
mistaken, here  and that there’s no other way to
ошибаюсь вот а что по-другому нельзя
earn money there, it’s somehow hard for you.
заработать там у вас как-то тяжело
I don’t know, he’s just such an
Я не знаю он просто сам по себе такой
interesting person in himself, so he
человек достаточно интересный вот он
said that his father fought, so he’ll
сказал что у него отец воевал значит он
go too, I don’t know, in short, Propaganda
тоже пойдёт не знаю короче Пропаганда
has brainwashed, it’s clear that people are going to die.
промыла мозги видно и люди идут умирать
Perhaps  Yes And how do you feel about this in general? You’re
Возможно да А вы как вообще к этому
not afraid of all this. It’s
относитесь не боитесь этого всего
scary, of course it’s scary. Why is this?
Страшно конечно страшно А почему это Вот
Because I’m kind of from Moldova myself. Yes. From
потому что я как бы сам из Молдовы Да Из
Chisinau, like, I try to watch both
Кишинёва типа я стараюсь смотреть и
Ukrainian and Russian news, here
украинские новости и российские тут
I include in Char roulette with Ukrainians and
включаю в Ча рулетки с украинцами с
Russians, I communicate on  I set it up and
россиянами общаюсь онн ставил с
talked to the Ukrainians for 2 hours before that,
украинцами общался 2 часа перед этим
too, I can’t understand. Why is this war
тоже я не могу понять А зачем это война
going on at all in order to push back
вообще идёт для того чтобы отодвинуть
NATO troops, but I don’t understand what the point is
войска НАТО но я не понимаю в чём смысл
like Well, it’s clear
типа Ну понятное дело
that let’s say it all goes to Kiev, but
что допустим это всё до идёт до Киева но
how are they going to push back the troops?
как они собираются отодвигать войска
NATO Yes, and having reached Kiev I don’t understand Well,
НАТО Да и дойдя до Киева Я не понимаю Ну
even more so Latvia Lithuania Estonia
да тем более Латвия Литва Эстония
Finland This is all that is also in NATO, there are
Финляндия Это всё что тоже в НАТО там
just NATO troops in Ukraine there are
как раз войска НАТО есть в Украине войск
no NATO troops Why should they be pushed back there are
НАТО нет Что их отодвигать там
Ukrainian troops And I, too, I
украинские войска И я тоже вот я россиян
asked Russian friends, I say A  as you
знакомых спрашивал говорю А как вы
see, like, well, if you were near Kiev and
видите типа ну если вы были под Киевом и
you were kicked out of there, how do you want to
вас оттуда выгнали как Вы снова хотите
get there again? I don’t see all of this either.
туда добраться Я тоже не вижу этого
What do people say they are
всего А что у вас вот люди говорят
already tired of
устали уже от
this? Well, to be honest, this
этого Ну на нас это честно говоря
probably doesn’t really affect us
наверное не особо-то влияет
Well.  yes, yes, rather, well, taking into account the fact that
Ну да да скорее ну с учётом того что у
we have no one there, thank God, no one was
нас там никого нет слава Богу никого не
mobilized, the only thing I’m
мобилизовали единственное что вот я
saying is that the father of my close friend
говорю отца моей близкой подруги
was mobilized in the first wave, but
мобилизовали вот в первую волну самую но
she is from the Sverdlovsk region and
она из Свердловской области и у них
for some reason the Sverlovsk region
сверловская область почему-то очень
came under very strong
сильно попала под
mobilization Well, it’s just for me Sometimes it’s
мобилизацию Вот и Ну мне просто Иногда
hard to listen to her, it’s sad because I’m
тяжело её слушать грустно потому что я
worried about her, that’s why
переживаю вот
she doesn’t see her dad for a long time and all
что она там долго не видит папу и вс
that, but it doesn’t concern us, but in
такое но так нас это не касается но в
any case it’s scary when
любом случае это страшно когда долетают
some drones fly in, we see it all
какие-то беспилотники мы это всё видим У
I have a friend from Ukraine whom we
меня есть друг с Украины с которым мы
met on the
познакомились в
Internet about four years ago and
интернете сколько Года четыре назад и
when the war began. We didn’t believe in this,
когда началась война Мы не верили в это
we, that is, we were still in school then, it
мы то есть мы ещё в школе тогда
was very scary and painful to hear
с было очень страшно и больно услышать
from him. Well, I asked if it was true.
от него Ну я спросила правда ли это
in general, that’s what he told me: Yes, today
вообще вот и он мне сказал Да сегодня
my morning began with the words of my mother. Good
моё Утро началось со слов мамы Доброе
morning, the war has begun. That’s why, yes,
утро началась война Вот и поэтому Да
morally, it’s all hard and very
морально - это всё тяжело и очень
scary to realize that in the 21st century we
страшно осознавать что мы в XXI веке
live in the age of war. Unfortunately, I
живём в век войны К сожалению вот
won’t say the same if I tell  fortunately
но не скажу тоже если скажу к счастью
this doesn’t concern us it will be
что нас это не касается это будет
wrong in relation to other people
Неправильно по отношению к другим людям
but it’s hard to realize it’s
но это тяжело осознавать это
really scary and who knows how
действительно страшно и кто знает как
it will turn out later and what interests me most
это потом обернётся и меня больше всего
in this case is when the end
интересует в этом случае когда конец то
is so you can fight endlessly
есть Так можно воевать же бесконечно
absolutely this is scary  Why do you
абсолютно это вот это страшно А как вы
think this war started in the first place,
считаете из-за чего эта война вообще
because people
началась изза того что люди
apparently don’t know how to talk? I don’t know who you are, your friend is from Ukraine and you don’t know how to talk because of this, the war started, some specific people or what is obvious. Probably this is inability
очевидно Наверное это неумение
states to hear their
государств слышать свой
people because for states we are
народ потому что для государств мы
just like a mass without a voice
просто как масса без голоса
and democracy As a
и демократия Как
cover for
прикрытие
this state despite the creation of
это государство несмотря на создание
international law despite the
международного права несмотря на
creation of the
создание
UN They do not use this for rational
ООН Не используют это в рациональных
purposes for how it was created and how
целях для того как это создавалось и как
it should have been
это должно было
created Well, Specifically Well
создаваться Ну а Конкретно Ну виноваты
specific people are to blame. In
виноваты конкретные какие-то люди Вот в
this scheme, who is to blame there, Biden Angela
этой схеме кто виноват там байден Анжела
Merkel Angela Merkel who is to blame for
Меркель Ангела Меркель кто виноват в
this
этой
war, do you think here we can say that
войне вы думаете тут можно сказать что
one person is to blame nouveau Well, just name it, I
виноват один человек нуво Ну Назовите
’m interested, I’m collecting for me, I’m
просто вот мне интересно я собираю мне я
from Moldova, I see it in  to my own, yes, I’m
из Молдовы вижу это по-своему да Мне
interested, I ask the Ukrainians from the
интересно я у украинцев спрашиваю у
Russians how they see
Россиян как они видят
this in a set of states, if we talk about the
это в совокуп государств если говорить
first thing it’s worth saying about the economic
первое стоит сказать про экономическую
benefits, most likely the war is primarily
выгоду скорее всего война первым делом
beneficial to Great Britain because of the large
выгодна Великобритании из-за большого
number of
количества
weapons business there regarding
оружейных оружейного бизнеса там по
America.
Америки ю
I can’t do that  somehow, to be honest, it’s very
Я не могу это как-то если честно очень
far-fetched because I don’t
сильно притянуть за уши Потому что я не
understand US policy. To be
понимаю политику
honest, is Putin to blame? I also can’t
честно виноват ли Путин я я тоже не могу
answer this question because
на это ответить вопрос потому что
the demands to push back
требования о том чтобы отодвинуть войска
NATO troops He stated a long time ago but to make
НАТО Он заявлял давно но предпринять
some diplomatic attempts  Well,
какие-то дипломатические попытки Ну тоже
they were also undertaken, but somehow. That is, I
они предпринимались но както То есть я
correctly understand that it turns out that Great
правильно понимаю что это получается
Britain forced Putin to attack
Великобритания заставила Путина напасть
Ukraine like this. No, of course, but there is an
на Украину так Нет конечно но
economic basis here too,
экономическая подоплёка она здесь тоже
yes, well, I can’t understand, look,
есть да ну я не могу понять смотрите
if not, you want to say the question is
если нет вы хотите сказать именно вопрос
whether a certain person is to blame for that
виноват ли определённый человек в том
that a war has begun Well, I just
что началась война Ну я просто как
see it from Moldova, yes
смотрю я из Молдовы вижу это так да
Putin signed a decree on his Yes and he attacked
Путин подписал указ об сво Да и напал на
Ukraine, it turns out there is a
Украину получается есть
decree for a reason yes yes Well, if
указ не просто так да да Ну вот если бы
he had not attacked Ukraine there would not have been a war
он не напал на Украину войны бы не было
now it turns out from this  wars, Russians are dying
получается сейчас из этой войны умирают
in Russia, Ukrainians are in Ukraine, yes,
россияне в России украинцы в Украине да
that is, it turns out that Putin is playing to the tune of
то есть получается Путин играет по дудку
Great Britain and the
Великобритании и
USA No,
США Нет
of course, why
конечно так А зачем
not? Well, you understand that there was a
онда Ну вы же понимаете что была
provocation. What kind of provocation from NATO?
провокация Какая со стороны НАТО
What kind of
Какая том что
howling, where are NATO troops
воя где войска НАТО
standing?
стоят
Well, don’t look at NATO here  Poland was in NATO
Ну не смотрите НАТО вот в Польша в НАТО
Lithuania Latvia Estonia was Yes in Ukraine there
Литва Латвия Эстония была Да в Украине
was no NATO in Moldova We don’t have NATO either
было в Молдове У нас тоже нету НАТО
Where should they have raised the idea of ​​NATO joining
Откуда должны были о вступлении НАТО в
Ukraine, wait where should the troops
Украину поднима подожди откуда войска
have been moved back specifically from
должны были отодвинуть конкретно из
what area NATO should have withdrawn
какой области НАТО должно было вывести
its
свои
troops Ukraine wanted to join NATO
войска Украина хотела вступить в НАТО
wanted to join Yes, well, well, there
хотела вступить Да ну вот ну там войск
weren’t any troops there Why did Russia attack?
никаких не было Зачем Россия напала Ну
Well, Ukraine wanted to join NATO. Well, it wanted to. So what?
Украина хотела вступить в НАТО Ну хотела
Well, if Ukraine had joined NATO,
И что Ну если бы Украина вступила в НАТО
then the
то
troops would have been at the borders of Russia, and
что войска были бы у границ Росси а то
then Russia had no demand
то то требования у России не было
to push back the troops  Yes, it demanded that
отодвинуть войска Да требовало чтобы
Ukraine not join NATO, so
Украина не вступала в НАТО так
the demands were that by way of
требования было о том чтобы путём
Uh-huh Goodbye,
Угу До свидания
Glory to
Слава
Ukraine, I’ll
Украине
move the arohi Adrian the cunning mo Adrian
сдвину арохи Адриан хитрый мо Адриан
Popesku from
попеску из
Kishen so subscribe I don’t know how it’s done
кишене так подпишитесь не знаю как это
like subscribe
прон сда лайк подписка
comment subscribe to my Ista I don’t know
комент подпишись на мий Иста Я не знаю
what this is for  tob Why are you there to
для чего це тоб Для чего тоб там
marvel at omi face Ale for you tse
дивитись на оми фейс Але для тебе це
one two or three clicks Ale you trime
один два або три клика Але ты тримае
me me and I will be clita Wow in me there Kupa
мене и я буду клита Вау в мене там Купа
folov and in me there will be a cool mood to
фолов и в мене буде класный настрий щоб
robite nove cool video message on my
робите нове крут видео пись на мий
Instagram pop Andriy O
Instagram попк Андрий О
so come on
так давай
cell N
ячка N